Guide to the William Beckford Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Beckford collection
1735-1967
GEN MSS 102
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.46
(14 boxes)
The William Beckford Collection consists of correspondence, a few manuscripts, personal papers of Beckford family members, a 16mm motion picture film on Beckford with accompanying reel-to-reel soundtrack, and other papers relating to Beckford research and collections.
Other Storage Formats: Oversize
Beckford, William, 1760-1844
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was formed primarily from gifts by three noted Beckford collectors: James T. Babb, Rowland Burden-Muller, and Ray Livingston Murphy, with additional purchases.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 14: Restricted fragile material (motion picture film and sound recording). Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Scope and Contents
The William Beckford Collection consists of letters, manuscripts, documents, and printed material relating to the life and career of William Beckford (1760-1844) and the Beckford family. Beckford is best known as the author of the Oriental fantasy Vathek, a collector of fine books and art, and the builder of impressive homes at Fonthill-Gifford and Bath. The material in the collection spans the years 1737 to 1967, with the bulk of the material contemporary with Beckford's life.
The collection is divided into four series: I. Correspondence, II. Writings, III. Family Papers, and IV. Other Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, consists of correspondence written during Beckford's life and is divided into three subseries: Letters from William Beckford, Letters to William Beckford, and Third Party Correspondence. Letters from Beckford to family, friends, and acquaintances reveal much about his personal life and career. Many letters written from various European cities describe Beckford's travels and meetings with famous people.
Equally significant is the collection of letters from Beckford to his friend the Reverend Samuel Henley, the translator of Vathek into English. A number of letters between 1782 and 1784 discuss the writing and publication of Vathek and the succeeding "Episodes of Vathek." On November 18, 1783 he informs Henley concerning Vathek, "You have the only copy which exists of the only production of mine which I am not ashamed of & with which I am not disgusted. Thank God Vathek has produced no misunderstanding." He adds an note concerning his Dreams, Waking Thoughts and Incidents: "I may still dwell upon the recollection with pleasure; but how can I endure my book of Dreams when I reflect what disagreeable waking thoughts it has occasioned us...?"
Other letters to Henley implore him to take charge of the education of William Courtenay, the young boy whose association with Beckford caused an intense scandal in 1784. A letter of October 13, 1784, just after his visit to Courtenay at his home, Powderham Castle, alludes to this affair: "You must know we have been in Devonshire & passed a month at Powderham Castle, where I lived in one perpetual worry to use a nursery expression which I have caught at the above mentioned place." He later writes of this affair to Henley, "It is impossible for me to enter into details upon the subject you mention. Let it suffice for me to assure you--that the reports you hear are the grossest calumnies & that a certain young person I once thought my friend--has proved himself the meanest traytor [sic]--& the blackest enemy... ."
Series I also contains three bound volumes of copies of letters from Beckford to George Clarke, his principal book agent. These letters, written between 1830 and 1834, reveal Beckford's knowledge of authors, artists, and books and indicate both his own collecting interests and collecting trends of the early nineteenth century. His letters often become venomous in describing unscrupulous booksellers and collectors, especially those who have wronged him. Although his letters to Clarke primarily concern his book collecting, Beckford occasionally refers to Mozart and other acquaintances and to his own writing. At the end of the final volume of the Clarke correspondence is an incomplete attempt at a topical index.
Letters to H. E. Goodrich, the primary architect of Beckford's Lansdown Tower in Bath, concern the construction of this home and Beckford's tomb and reveal Beckford's knowledge of and attention to architectural details and decor.
A volume of letters to William Smith, Jr, printseller in London, discusses items Beckford had purchased or wished to purchase and discloses much about his interest and tastes in art, mentioning purchases of works by Titian, Van Dyck, Rubens, etc.
A rather lengthy letter to Sir William Hamilton reveals Beckford's quest or a peerage (December 15, 1800).
Letters to unidentified correspondents and copies of Beckford's letters collected by James T. Babb have been placed at the end of this subseries.
The Correspondence series also contains letters from a number of Beckford's contemporaries, many of whom offer revealing glimpses of Beckford or Fonthill. Letters from Thomas Adams to John Britton (September to November, 1823) speak of the sale of Fonthill Abbey and its effects. An undated letter from H. Austed to Britton says of Beckford, "It must seem very curious to some people to be one day told that a man is totally ruined & in a week in the same paper that he is about to level a great hill or if that is not practicable to raise a Saxon tower to reach the clouds in order to obtain a view of his former residence... ." There is also a rather vitriolic exchange of letters between Britton, the author of Graphical and Literary Illustrations of Fonthill Abbey, and his illustrator George Cattermole concerning Cattermole's sketches for this work.
Series II, Writings, consists of writings by Beckford and Elizabeth Hervey, his half-sister. Included are a copy of a portion of Beckford's diary, two short poems by Beckford, and two copies of Hervey's novel Julia.
Series III, Personal Papers, consists of statements of indenture for several members of the Beckford family, a copy of Beckford's will, and items relating to the building of Fonthill Abbey.
Series IV, Other Papers, consists of various types of material on a number of subjects relating to Beckford, arranged alphabetically by subject. Included are genealogical and biographical information on Beckford and his family; articles on Beckford, his homes, and his writings; prints and photographs of Beckford, his father, Fonthill Abbey, and Lansdown Tower; and correspondence among Beckford collectors and booksellers. The file on Fonthill Abbey is especially rich, with many late eighteenth- and nineteenth-century articles, contemporary descriptions, and sketches. The file on Vathek contains articles and notes on the publishing history of Beckford's most significant work. The Rowland Burdon-Miller correspondence file has a number of letters from noted book collector and author John Carter. Filed at the end of the series is a 16mm motion picture film on Beckford, accompanied by a reel-to-reel audio tape soundtrack and documentation. The film features scenes associated with William Beckford in Bath, England. The film was planned and produced by Andrew Barnett and Alan Scott, students at the Kingswood School in Bath, during the 1966 Bath Festival which was devoted to Beckford.
Architecture, Domestic -- England; Architecture, Gothic; Art -- Collectors and collecting; English fiction -- 18th century; English literature -- 18th century; Fantasy in literature; Private libraries -- England; Travel; Bath (England) -- History; England -- Antiquities; England -- Intellectual life -- 18th century; Europe -- Description and travel -- Early works to 1800; Europe -- Description and travel; Lansdown Tower; Audiovisual materials; Motion pictures (visual works); Sound recordings; Authors, English -- 19th century; Book collectors; Travelers -- England; Beckford, William, 1709-1770; Beckford, William, 1760-1844; Britton, John, 1771-1857; Carter, John, 1905-1975; Cattermole, George, 1800-1868; Clark, John; Hamilton, William, Sir, 1730-1803; Henley, Samuel, 1740-1815; Wyatt, James, 1746-1813; Fonthill Abbey
- Correspondence, 1750-1950; Series I; 1.75; (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, consists of letters to and from William Beckford and third-party correspondence among Beckford's contemporaries.
  - LETTERS FROM WILLIAM BECKFORD
    - Adams, Henry, 1832 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Barclay, Robert, 1807-16 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
    - Beckford, Louisa (typescripts, photocopies), [1780-84] (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Beckford, Susan, 1805-08 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Bohn, Henry G., 1840, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Britton, John, 1823, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - Clarke, George
      - 2 ALS, 1813, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8a)
      - "Letters of William Beckford to His Bookseller, 1830-1834" [transcribed for, then corrected by Richard Bentley]
        - Description of the letters, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Bound volumes (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
        - Bound volume (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - Related material, 1900-50 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Clarke, [William], 1829 Feb 22 (Box 2, Folder 13a)
    - Cozens, Alexander (holograph original and photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - English, Edmund, 1825, 1841 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Box 3, folder 50
    - Fraser's Magazine, 1833 Mar 21 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Goodrich, H. E. (thirteen letters from Beckford, bound in folder), 1825-42 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Gore, Catherine, [1839?] (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Green, Thomas A., 1797 Jun 4 (Box 2, Folder 19a)
    - Hamilton, Anne, Lady, 1805 Oct 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Hamilton, Emma Lyon, Lady, 1800, 1808 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      See also: Box 7, folder 140
    - Hamilton, Susan, Duchess of [?] (letter in French, with typed translation), 1823 Apr 11 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Hamilton, William, Sir, 1782-1800 (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
    - Henley, Samuel, Rev., 1782-97, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26-32)
    - Holford, Mr., 1841 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Jennings, Robert, 1839, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Lennings, Mr. (Jennings?), 1838 Sep 1 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Mayne, John Thomas, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Molteno & Graves, 1834 (Box 2, Folder 36a)
    - Morlands, Auriol, and Co. (Duckett, Morlands, and Co.) (mainly checks), 1814-32 (Box 2, Folder 37-43)
    - [Murray, Charles Augustus], [1839?] (Box 2, Folder 43a)
    - Nelson, Horatio, Lord (with typescript copy), 1801 Apr 29 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Pedley, John, 1835 Jan 30 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Phillipps, Thomas, Baronet, 1811 Dec 1 (Box 3, Folder 45a)
    - Pinkerton, Mr., 1800 Sep 18 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Pratt, S. T., 1797 Mar 18 (Box 3, Folder 46a)
    - Reade, John Edmund, 1840 Jan 12 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Reddings, Mr., 1835 Sep 16 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Smith, Acheson (envelope only), 1818 May 22 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Smith, John, [1824?] Apr 24 (Box 3, Folder 49a)
    - Smith, Messrs. (art dealers?). (Bound volume of 45 letters from Beckford, with letters from L. Beckett, letters to Edmund English, documents, etc.), 1769-1844 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Smith, Mr., 1841, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Still, S. C., 1811 May 30 (Box 3, Folder 51a)
    - Tacet, Monsieur, 1792 Jul 22 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Tiffin, Mr., 1836 Jun 29 (Box 3, Folder 52a)
    - Vyse, William. ALS (engraving), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 52b)
      With: engraving of Beckford as mayor of London.
    - White, A. L., 1842 Jul 6 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Unidentified letters from Beckford, 1818-41 (Box 3, Folder 54-55)
    - Miscellaneous notes from Beckford, 1814, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Miscellaneous letters from Beckford (typescripts and photocopies) (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - LETTERS TO WILLIAM BECKFORD
    - Beckford, Louisa (typescript copies and photocopies), 1782-89, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 58-61)
    - Beckford, Louisa (typescript copies and photocopies), 1782-89, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 62-65)
    - Bohn, Henry G., 1842 Jul 14 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Britton, John (with engraving of Britton), 1837 Jun 21 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - DeStarck, Henry Savile, 1812 Aug (Box 4, Folder 67a)
    - Franchi, L. (with pencil notes by Beckford and typescript copy with translation), 1822 Feb 24 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Seymour, Georgina Seymour, Henry (typescript copies with letter from T. M. Lewis), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Wyatt, Anthony, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Adams, Thomas
      - Letter to John Britton, 1823 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Anspach, (Elizabeth), Margravine of, (Lady Craven)
      - Letter to Sir William Hamilton, 1789 (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - Letter to unknown recipient, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Austed, H.
      - Letter to John Britton, [n.y.] Oct 14 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Beckford, Peter
      - Letters to Rev. Samuel Henley, [1783?] (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Beckford, Susan
      - Letters to Lady Bellhaven, [1820] (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Beckford, William (1709 to 1770)
      - Letters to John Curtis (with engraving and clipping), 1765-66 (Box 4, Folder 77-78)
      - Letter to Thomas, Stephen and Rose Fullers, 1777 Apr 26 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      - Letter to Mr. Granville, 1766 Jun 2 (Box 4, Folder 80)
      - Letter to John Kirke, 1754 May 25 (Box 4, Folder 81)
      - Letter to Roffey and Chamberlin, 1756 Dec (Box 4, Folder 82)
      - Letter to Thomas and Stephen Tulley, 1757 Oct 3 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - Letters to unidentifed recipients, 1736-68 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Britton, John
      - Letter to Thomas Adams, 1823 (Box 4, Folder 85)
      - Letter to Richard Bentley, 1835 Jan 8 (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - Letter to George Cattermole, 1822 Nov 15 (Box 4, Folder 87)
      - Letter to S. C. Hall, 1852 May 18 (Box 4, Folder 88)
      - Letter to William Upcott, 1824 Feb 18 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Cattermole, George
      - Letters to John Britton, 1822, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Hamilton, William, Sir
      - Letter to Mr. Cadell (with engraving of Hamilton), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Higham, Thomas
      - Letter to John Britton (with Britton's response), 1827 Oct 13 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Lettice, John
      - Letter to Clarke and Son, Booksellers, 1826 Dec 6 (Box 4, Folder 93)
      - Letter to Samuel Henley, 1805 Sep 15 (Box 4, Folder 94)
      - Letter to John Pinkerton, 1800 Aug 20 (Box 4, Folder 95)
      - Letter to Isaac Reed, 1797 Jul 11 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Sharp, Richard
      - Letter to Rev. Samuel Henley, 1786 Jun 14 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Stanhope, Hester Lucy, Lady
      - Letter to Sir Isaac Heard, 1800 Oct 22 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Trumbull, Col. [John?]
      - Letters to Jeremiah Wadsworth (typescript and photostat copies, with letter from Theodore Sizer to James T. Babb), 1798-99 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Watts, A. A.
      - Letter to John Britton, 1824 Jan 19 (Box 4, Folder 100)
- Writings, 1803-34; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series II, Writings, consists of writings by William Beckford and his half-sister, Elizabeth Hervey.
  - WILLIAM BECKFORD
    - Diary: typescript copy (pages numbered 276-280 only), n. d. (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Italy, with Sketches of Spain and Portugal (excerpt: "Visit to the Escurial"). The Mirror, 1834 Sep 27 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - [Notes on the coming of Christ] (authorship uncertain), 1837 Feb 21 (Box 5, Folder 102a)
    - "O Astra. O Coelum": photocopy, 1800 Oct (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - "Ode" ("Written by Mr. Beckford at the Grand Chartreuse"): holograph (in Beckford's hand?) (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - "Sir Squashaline" (unpublished poem by Beckford): typescript copy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - ELIZABETH HERVEY
    - Julia (2 copies), 1803 (Box 5, Folder 106-07)
- Personal Papers, 1735-1844; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series III, Personal Papers, includes statements of indenture for various members of the Beckford family, a copy of William Beckford's will, and items relating to Fonthill Abbey.
  - Deed of sale for land in America: photocopy, 1789 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Drawings by William Beckford: Two landscapes and one sketch of Governor Loo (in pencil and ink), 1836, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 108a)
  - Drawing by William Beckford's daughter: Two houses (in pencil on letter addressed to Mr. James Orde), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 108b)
  - Fonthill Abbey
    - Statement of expenses for work at Fonthill by John Soane, 1787-88 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - "Lists of Plate.. .Belonging to William Beckford... .": holograph notebook, 1818 (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - Watercolor sketch of bridge and roadway by James Wyatt (with fragment of note by Beckford on verso) (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Indentures
    - Bond of William Beckford (1709 - 1770) to Thomas Beckford, 1735 Oct 20 (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - Bond of Bathsua Beckford to Thomas Beckford, 1743 (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - Bond of Francis Beckford to Thomas Beckford, 1749 Aug 24 (Box 6, Folder 114)
      EMPTY FOLDER: Material transferred to Oversize boxes: Box 12, folder 268
    - Bond of Julius Beckford to Francis Beckford, 1754 Dec 19 (Box 6, Folder 115)
      EMPTY FOLDER: Material transferred to Oversize boxes: Box 13, folder 276
  - Bond of William Beckford and others to John Balaguier, 1756 Mar 30 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - William Beckford (1709-1770): Portrait (in oil) by Marcellus Laroon, n.d. (Box art, Folder 116a)
  - William Beckford (1760-1844): Last will and testament (photocopy, with typescript), 1844 Oct 1 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Francis Beckford(?): signature, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 118)
- Other Papers, 1755-1967; Series IV; 2.21; (6 boxes)
  Series IV, Other Papers, consists primarily of writings about Beckford and his homes, prints and photographs of Fonthill Abbey and Lansdown Tower; correspondence of Beckford collectors James T. Babb and Rowland Burdon-Muller; and a 16mm motion picture film on Beckford with accompanying reel-to-reel soundtrack and documentation.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 14: Restricted fragile material (motion picture film and sound recording). Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Account book (unidentified, with information about Beckford's lease of Schodelhan Farm)
    See: Oversize, Box 12, folder 269
  - Babb Collection
    - Inventories, 1963-67 (Box 7, Folder 119-20)
    - "Want List", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Beckford Library: disposition lists
    - Barnbougle Castle
      Related Materials
      See: Oversize, Box 12, folders 270-71
    - Clements Library: catalogue of Beckford books, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - Clements Library: sale catalogue, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 123)
    - Gennadius Library: typescript list, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Bodleain Library Beckford Desiderata list, Bodleain Quarterly Record, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Biographical sketch, 1888 (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Booksellers' catalogues, 1933-53, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 127-30)
  - Booksellers' invoices, 1929-48 (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - Burdon-Muller collection: miscellaneous notes, 1933, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - Correspondence: James T. Babb
    - Alexander, Boyd, 1949-65 (Box 7, Folder 133-35)
    - "B" general, 1933-60 (Box 7, Folder 136)
    - Boston Public Library, 1956-57 (Box 7, Folder 137)
    - Burdon-Muller, Rowland, 1933-66 (Box 7, Folder 138-39)
    - "C" general, 1933-42 (Box 7, Folder 140)
    - Chapman, Guy, 1933-39 (Box 7, Folder 141)
    - Clements, Colonel H. T. W., 1957-58 (Box 7, Folder 142)
    - "E-H" general, 1936-61 (Box 7, Folder 143)
    - Harrowby Manuscript Trust (Earl of Harrowby), 1961 (Box 7, Folder 144)
    - Hobson, Anthony, 1957-59 (Box 7, Folder 145)
    - Holburne of Menstrie Museum of Art, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 146)
    - "I-M" general, 1934-64 (Box 7, Folder 147)
    - Murphy, Ray Livingston, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 148)
    - Oliver, John W., 1933 Jan 5 (Box 7, Folder 149)
    - "P-R" general, 1937-61 (Box 7, Folder 150)
    - Rosebery, Eva, Lady, 1960-65 (Box 7, Folder 151)
    - "S" general, 1957-66 (Box 7, Folder 152)
    - Summers, Peter G., 1965-66 (Box 7, Folder 153)
    - "T-Z" general, 1957-60 (Box 7, Folder 154)
  - Correspondence: Rowland Burdon-Muller
    - Booksellers' Correspondence, 1933-42 (Box 7, Folder 155-57)
  - Correspondence: Others
    - Bennett, Arnold, 1910 Oct 16 (Box 7, Folder 158)
    - Timbs, John (letter about Vathek ), 1959 Jun 30 (Box 7, Folder 159)
  - Exhibitions
    - Holburne Museum (Bath), 1966 (Box 8, Folder 160)
    - Yale University, 1959-60 (Box 8, Folder 161)
  - Fonthill Abbey: Articles and Newspaper Clippings
    - "Fonthill." The Adventurer of the Nineteenth Century, 1823 Jun 28 (Box 8, Folder 162)
    - "Fonthill Abbey." The Mirror of Literature, Amusement, and Instruction, 1826 Jan 28 (Box 8, Folder 163)
    - [Fonthill Abbey]. The Mirror of literature, Amusement, and Instruction, 1826 Jul 15 (Box 8, Folder 164)
    - "Fonthill Abbey and Domain," Evans and Ruffy Farmer's Journal, 1822 Oct 21
      See: Oversize, Box 12, folder 272
    - "Fonthill Mansion, Wilts, to be sold... ." The Courier, 1807 Aug 11 (Box 8, Folder 165)
      EMPTY FOLDER: Material transferred to Oversize boxes: Box 13, folder 277
    - "Fonthill, Wiltshire" (articles by John Harris and Boyd Alexander). Country Life, 1966 Nov-Dec (Box 8, Folder 166)
    - "Fonthill, Wiltshire.", n.d. (Box 8, Folder 167)
    - "Fonthill-Gifford" (topographical dictionary entries), 1837, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 168)
    - Garbett-Archt, W. "Remarks on the Architecture of Fonthill Abbey." Holograph (marked "Gents Mag."), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 169)
    - Lewis, Kensington. "Fonthill Abbey--The Topaz Vase." Advertisement to the Editor of The Morning Chronicle (holograph), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 170)
      EMPTY FOLDER: Material transferred to Oversize boxes: Box 12, folder 273
    - "Magnificent and Valuable Effects, Fonthill to be Sold by Auction...," The Sun, 1801 Jul 27 (Box 8, Folder 171)
      EMPTY FOLDER: Material transferred to Oversize boxes: Box 13, folder 278
    - Mayhew, Edgar. "A View of Fonthill Abbey." Register of the Museum of Art of the University of Kansas, 1957 Dec (Box 8, Folder 172)
    - "Sale of the Beckford Collection." The Illustrated London News, 1845
      See: Oversize, Box 12, folder 274
    - Storer, James. Description of Fonthill Abbey, Wiltshire., 1812 (Box 8, Folder 173)
    - "Strange Freaks of a Millionaire." Exeter News-Letter, 1859 Feb 28 (Box 8, Folder 174)
      EMPTY FOLDER: Material transferred to Oversize boxes: Box 13, folder 279
    - Collection of contemporary notes and published articles on Fonthill and William Beckford, kept by John Britton (Box 8, Folder 175)
    - Magazine excerpts and descriptive notes on Fonthill Abbey, with partial list of items sold at auction (collected by John Britton?), 1822-23, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 176)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1755-1960 (Box 8, Folder 177-78)
  - Fonthill Abbey: related material
    - EMPTY FOLDER (Box 8, Folder 179)
    - Description of Fonthill Abbey (by unidentified author). Holograph, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 180)
    - "List of Subscribers to Fonthill" (letters copied by John Britton), [1822?] (Box 8, Folder 181)
    - "Plan and Survey of the Estate of William Beckford, Esq... .", [1800?] (Box 8, Folder 182)
    - Price list for books at Fonthill Sale (of Fonthill Abbey). Holograph, 1780, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 183)
    - Prints and Photographs
      - "A view at Fonthill Abbey" (with dwarf), (lithograph), n.d.
        See: Oversize, Box 13, folder 280
      - Collection of sketches and descriptions (collected by John Britton?), 1823, nd. (Box 9, Folder 184)
      - Colored engraving (print) by H. R. Havell and Son; drawn by H. Gartineau from sketch by T. Higham